{"tossups": [{"question": "The Ruthven Raid kidnapped this monarch who wrote<em> Basilikon Doron</em> and the<em> True Law of Free</em> <em>Monarchies</em>. He attempted to arrange a marriage between his son and the Infanta Maria in the Spanish Match and was called \u201cthe wisest fool in Christendom\u201d. This king faced the Bye Plot and an assassination attempt carried out by Roger Catesby and Guy Fawkes known as the Gunpowder Plot. For the point, name this first Stuart King of England who commissioned a namesake Bible.", "answer": "<b> James I</b> of England or<b> James VI</b> of Scotland", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The third movement scherzo of this piece includes a repeat which is often ignored, and a statement of its first movement\u2019s second subject is often played by the horns instead of the bassoons. This composition\u2019s opening motif was used by BBC Radio during World War II as part of its \u201cV for Victory\u201d campaign, and was described by its composer as \u201cfate knocking on the door\u201d. For the point, name this symphony by Ludwig van Beethoven that opens with a \u201cshort-short-short-long\u201d rhythm.", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven</b>\u2019s<b> Symphony</b> no. <b>5</b> in C minor, Op.", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The Wilson-Gorman Revenue Act scaled back a tariff passed by this man, who earned the nickname the\u201cNapoleon of Protection.\u201d He employed campaign manager Mark Hanna for two successful \u201cfront-porch\u201dcampaigns against William Jennings Bryan. Hawaii was annexed by this president, who passed the Gold Standard Act to end bimetallism. For the point, name this 25th U.S. President, who was succeeded by Theodore Roosevelt.", "answer": "William<b> McKinley</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Arcadio Huang served as a Chinese translator to this monarch, who gave slaves the right to marry with his Code Noir. His invasion of the Free County of Burgundy started the War of Devolution. The Fronde opposed this monarch internally, and his foreign expansionism was opposed by William of Orange\u2019s League of Augsburg. For the point, name this French monarch who revoked the Edict of Nantes by issuing the Edict of Fontainebleau and was nicknamed \u201cthe Sun King.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Louis XIV</b> of France", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In a series of speeches to American troops, this man called a man fixing a telegraph wire in Africa the bravest he\u2019d met. He won a race to Messina against his British counterpart Bernard Montgomery. This leader of the fictitious First U.S. Army Group saw his career stall after slapping a fatigued soldier. The Third Army was commanded after D-Day by, for the point, what American general known as \u201cOld Blood and Guts?\u201d", "answer": "George S.<b> Patton</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Members of this party formed the Barnwell Ring. Its rival used the \u201cSouthern Strategy\u201d to convert members of this party. One leader of this party reportedly claimed that it had \u201clost the South for a generation\u201d after he signed the Civil Rights Act of 1964, and this party\u2019s Presidential nominee has only won South Carolina once since 1960. For the point, name this American political party opposed by the Republicans.", "answer": "<b> Democrat</b>ic Party", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "These people defeated Emperor Alexios I at the Battle of Dyrrhachium [dir-RAKE-ee-um] while led by Robert Guiscard [gee-scar], who had earlier been made Duke of Apulia and conquered the Emirate of Sicily. Their leader Rollo signed the treaty of St. Claire-sur-Epte after capturing Rouen, which granted them their namesake territory. The most famous leader of these people landed at Pevensey to dispute the inheritance of Edward the Confessor. For the point, name these people who won the Battle of Hastings under William the Conqueror.", "answer": "<b> Normans</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The<em> USS Washington</em> captured this ship, whose passengers had traveled aboard the<em> Tecora</em> to Cuba. Don Pedro Montez navigated this ship to Long Island, disobeying the orders of Sengbe Pieh. The Mende people aboard this ship were defended by John Quincy Adams, who convinced the Supreme Court to re-grant them their freedom. For the point, name this ship, on which a group of slaves revolted in 1839.", "answer": "La<b> Amistad</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The narrator of one poem set during this war delivers a cry to \u201ctake up our quarrel with the foe;\u201dthat poem\u2019s title location is marked with \u201ccrosses/row on row.\u201d An attack during this war was described in \u201cDulce et Decorum Est\u201d by Wilfred Owen, who died during this war. \u201cInsensibility\u201d describes soldiers in this war suffering from shell shock. John McCrae\u2019s \u201cIn Flanders Fields\u201d was set during, for the point, what \u201cGreat War\u201d fought from 1914 to 1919?", "answer": "<b> World War I</b> (accept the<b> Great</b> War until mentioned)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "In 2008, this country launched the Vision 2030 development program under Mwaki Kibaki. In the Goldenberg scandal, this country subsidized possibly non-existent gold exports, as authorized by President Daniel arap Moi. In 2013, its capital city\u2019s Westgate Shopping Mall was attacked by al-Shabaab, based in neighboring Somalia. For the point, name this African country, where Uhuru Kenyatta leads from Nairobi.", "answer": "<b> Kenya</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "For the point, what company delivered mail to California on its namesake steeds?", "answer": "<b> Pony Express</b> (or<b> Central Overland California and Pike\u2019s Peak Express Company</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This colony repelled a Spanish invasion as part of the War of Jenkins\u2019 Ear in the Battle of Bloody Marsh. Its charter prohibited slavery unitl 1749, and the Altamaha River was its original southern boundary. This colony was originally envisioned as a haven for debtors and \u201cthe worthy poor,\u201d by its founder, who established its first capital at Savannah. For the point, James Oglethorpe founded what province in 1732, the southernmost of the original Thirteen Colonies?", "answer": "Province of<b> Georgia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While serving as an intelligence officer in this country, Jean-Marie le Pen was accused of torture. This country\u2019s FLN, led by Ahmed Ben Bella, fought a guerilla war against its colonial rulers; after that war, Harkis and Pieds-Noirs [pee-ay nwar] fled this country as the Evian Accords granted it its independence in 1962. For the point, name this north African country, a former French colony with capital Algiers.", "answer": "People\u2019s Democratic Republic of<b> Algeria</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The \u201cH\u201d on the jersey from one of this city\u2019s sports teams is erroneously thought to represent early settlers of this city, the \u201cHabitants.\u201d Like San Diego, this city was awarded a National League MLB team in 1969; that team\u2019s name referenced the 1967 World\u2019s Fair held in this city. Until they moved to Washington, D.C., the Expos played in the Stade Olympique [STAHD oh-lim-PEEK] in, for the point, what French-speaking Canadian city?", "answer": "<b> Montreal</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s Presidency, Caleb Cushing signed the Treaty of Wanghia with the Qing Dynasty. John Botts tried to impeach this man, who was elected to the Confederate House of Representatives after his presidency. This Whig ran as Vice President in 1840 with the winner of the Battle of Tippecanoe. For the point, name this man who was dubbed \u201chis Accidency\u201d when he became President after William Henry Harrison\u2019s death.", "answer": "John<b> Tyler</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man helped raise money for a Central Park sculpture of Shakespeare by joining his brothers, Junius and Edwin, for a production of<em> Julius Caesar</em>. He plotted to kidnap a man at the Old Soldiers\u2019Home with the help of David Herold and George Atzerodt. One accomplice of this man, Lewis Powell, stabbed William Seward the same night that this man shouted \u201csic semper tyrannis!\u201d while leaping from the box at Ford\u2019s Theater. For the point, name this assassin of Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "John Wilkes<b> Booth</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Matthew Restall disputes claims that this empire\u2019s fall was due to its superstition regarding their conquerors arriving at the end of a 52-year cycle. The Tepanec War led to a Triple Alliance of this empire\u2019s cities, including Tlacopan. La Malinche [mah-LEEN-chay] helped one man conquer this empire, whose leader died during La Noche Triste [NO-chay TREEST]. Montezuma II was the final ruler of this empire from its capital at Tenochtitlan [ten-oach-TEET-lan], on modern Mexico City. For the point, name this Mesoamerican empire that was conquered by Hernan Cortes.", "answer": "<b> Aztec</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A group of hardliners sought to overthrow this leader in the August Coup. He attempted to reform his nation\u2019s economy by instituting perestroika and advocated for \u201copenness\u201d with glasnost. He renounced the Brezhnev Doctrine, which led to the fall of the Berlin Wall and the \u201cFall of Communism\u201d in 1989 across Eastern Europe. For the point, name this last General Secretary of the USSR.", "answer": "Mikhail<b> Gorbachev</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The difference in the sun\u2019s height at noon between two cities in this modern-day country led Eratosthenes to calculate the circumference of the Earth; other Greek mathematicians who lived in this region included Hypatia, Heron, and Euclid. For the point, name this country where many scientific texts were kept but lost in the burning of the library of Alexandria.", "answer": "<b> Egypt</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}], "bonuses": []}